Walter Savage Landor Correspondence, 1797-1887: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
Walter Savage Landor Correspondence
1797-1887
C0254
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
0.20 linear feet 1 half-size archival box
Landor, Walter Savage, 1775-1864.
Walter Savage Landor was an English poet and prose writer. This correspondence includes some of his letters to family members and friends and a collection of transcribed letters to and from Landor.
Walter Savage Landor, an English poet and prose writer, is best remembered for his work Imaginary Conversations.
The collection contains some of Landor's correspondence with family members and friends, including holograph letters (1836-1864) to his brother Henry Eyres Landor, to his sister Elizabeth, and to his nieces Ellen and Kitty, as well as several letters to Lady Blessington, Leigh Hunt, and John Edmund Reade. There are also original letters by Matthew Arnold, Lady Blessington, Shirley Brooks, George Jacob Holyoake, and John Morley, and 20 letters (1865-70) by John Forster and his wife to Landor's niece on the subject of Forster's biography of Landor.
In addition, there are about 200 pages of letters to and from Landor (1795-1864), transcribed in 1930-1931 from the originals when they were in the possession of Rev. Rasleigh Edmund Hungerford Duke, a relation of Landor. Most are addressed to or from family members, and approximately half relate to Landor's brother Henry.
Further accessions include additional correspondence and manuscripts connected with his contribution to The Atlas newspaper. Correspondents include Landor's daughter, Lady Blessington, G. P. R. James, William Charles Macready, and Edward Moxon. Also included are transcripts of original letters (1797-1862) which, formerly in the possession of the firm of Walter T. Spencer of London, were lost when the ship carrying them sank on its war to Princeton, N.J., in December 1940.
Collection is open for research use.
Gift of Prof. Robert H. Super '35.
Landor, Henry Eyres, 1780-1866 -- Correspondence.; Landor, Walter Savage, 1775-1864 -- Family.; Authors, English -- 19th century -- Correspondence.; Poets, English -- 19th century -- Correspondence.; Correspondence -- 19th century.; Manuscripts -- 19th century.; British literature
- Landor, Henry E, 1836-1851; 8 letters (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Landor, Elizabeth (sister) / Duke, Ellen Landor (niece) / Landor, Kitty (niece), 1849-1864; 27 letters (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous, 1826-1856; 11 letters
  - Lady Blessington, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Reade, J., undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hunt, Leigh, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hare, Mrs., undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Editor of Times, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - unidentified, undated; portion of 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Copies of letters, made 1930-1931 by Landor, Walter Noble; transcripts copied, 1849, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Arnold, Matthew, circa 1873-1885; 3 letters (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Blessington, Marguerite Gardiner, Countess of, 1837; 1 letter (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Brooks, Shirley, 1856; 1 letter (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Forster, John, 1865-1870; 25 letters (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Holynake, George Jacob, 1867; 1 letter (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Kinglake, Arthur, 1855; 1 letter (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Landor, Robert Eyres (brother), undated; 2 letters and other misc. matter (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Linton, Eliza Lynn, 1871; 1 letter (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Morley, John, 1872; 1 letter (Box 1, Folder 13)
- ALS to William Charles Macready, undated; 1 letter (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Transcripts of letters, 1797-1862; 6 letters (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Holograph Mss and letters connected to Landor's contribution to The Atlas newspaper, 1855; 8 items (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Transcripts of a letter for a scheme for the aid of Ireland, 1947 January 26; 1 letter (Box 1, Folder 17)
- ALS to Lady Blessington, 1843; 1 letter (Box 1, Folder 18)
- ALS to his daughter, undated; 1 letter (Box 1, Folder 19)
- ALS to Edward Moxon, 1846 June 13; 1 letter (Box 1, Folder 20)
- ALS to G. P. R. James, undated; 1 letter (Box 1, Folder 21)
- ALs to an unidentified recipient, undated; 1 letter (Box 1, Folder 22)